Finding Aid for W. Wallace Kent papers, 1954-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
W. Wallace Kent papers 1954-1973, 1969-1973
Kent, W. Wallace (William Wallace), 1916-1973.
19 linear feet
85243 Aa 2
Kalamazoo, Michigan, attorney; U. S. District Judge, 1954-1970, in the Western District, Michigan; judge U. S. Court of Appeals, 6th Circuit, 1971-1973. Case docket sheets, judges' case files, unpublished opinions, judges' memoranda, Court of Appeals panel reports, Court of Appeals Circuit Council reports; cases relate in part to school desegregation, Indian treaty rights, labor relations, and questions of civil liberties.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mrs. William Wallace Kent (Donor No. 5426 ) donated the papers in 1973.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Judge William Wallace Kent, 1916-1973, was born in Galesburg, Michigan, May 1, 1916. His parents were Harold C. and Alice W. (Budd) Kent. Judge Kent graduated from Western Michigan College, B.A., 1937, and received the J.D. from University of Michigan, 1940. He served as Assistant Prosecuting Attorney and Friend of the Court, Kalamazoo County, Michigan, 1941-1944, and Prosecuting Attorney, 1945-1946. He practiced law in Kalamazoo from 1946 until 1954, when he was appointed Federal District Court Judge for the Western District of Michigan. Judge Kent was appointed as Chief Judge of the Western District of Michigan in 1962, and retained that position until 1970, when he was appointed to the Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals. Judge Kent was affiliated with the Legal Aid Bureau, the Family Service Center and the Kalamazoo City Bar Association. He was a Mason, serving as Grand Master for Michigan, 1960-1961, and Grand Treasurer. Judge Kent married M. LaVerne Fredlund, July 7, 1940.
Judge William Wallace Kent's papers document his activities as a Federal Judge. The legal papers in the collection cover the years 1954 to 1973 and include a wide range of documents and records including Docket sheets, Alphabetical Index Cards, Docket Number Index Cards, Judges Case Files, Unpublished Opinions, Judges Memoranda, Hearings, Memoranda, Orders, Opinions, Court of Appeals Panel Reports, and Court of Appeals Circuit Council Meeting Documents.
The collection was maintained in its original order with three series: Case and Subject Index; District Court records; and Court of Appeals records.
Subjects:
Davis, Chandler.; Freemasonry--Michigan.; Indians of North America--Treaties.; Judges--Michigan.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Kent, W. Wallace (William Wallace), 1916-1973.; Law.; School integration--Michigan.; United States. Court of Appeals (6th Circuit); United States. District Court (Michigan: Western District)
- Case and Subject Index
  The Case and Subject Index series contains Docket Sheets, arranged by civil and criminal dockets. The Sheets have been kept in numerical order (with gaps). They are not necessarily in chronological order. The Alphabetical Index Cards for the District Court provide an entry into the Docket Sheets by the name of the party first listed in the case, normally the plaintiff. Docket Sheets include a docket number assigned to the case, the names of the parties involved and their attorneys, the nature of the case and brief remarks about actions taken by the court. The Docket Number Index Cards for the Court of Appeals includes the names of the parties involved, the judges, and the citations to published opinions. This series also includes a small amount of biographical material about Kent.
  - District Courts
    - Civil Docket Sheets (Box 1)
    - Civil Docket Sheets (cont.) (Box 2)
    - Criminal Docket Sheets (Box 2)
  - Alphabetical Index Cards (Box 2)
  - Docket Number Index Cards (Box 2)
  - Biographical Sketch and photograph (Kent) (Box 2)
- District Court 1954-1970
  The District Court Series consists of case files, arranged numerically by docket number. The case files include unbound papers filed in the proceedings, such as briefs, motions, opinions and correspondence. The Case Files relate to Habeas Corpus petitions by state prisoners and Constitutional or Statutory litigation involving such issues as refusal to testify before the House Un-American Activities Committee (Horace Chandler Davis v. United States, box 10), school desegregation (Berry v. Benton Harbor School District, box 3, or Bradley v. Milliken, boxes 11 and 18), unfair labor relations (Benton Harbor Malleable Industries v. United Auto Aircraft and Agricultural Implement Workers of America, box 8), or Indian treaty rights (L'Anse, Ontonagon, and Vieux Desert bands of the Chippewa Indians of Lake Superior v. Michigan Conservation Department, box 5). The majority of the Judges Case Files reflected cases based on personal injury, breach of contract, and other actions based on the diversity jurisdiction of the Federal Court, involving parties from different states. The Docket Sheets can be used to determine the types of documents filed in these cases, the lawyers and parties involved, and the length or complexity of such cases.
  - Judge's Case Files
    - Civil Docket, Cases 7-59 (Box 3)
    - Civil Docket, Cases 101-499 (Box 4)
    - Civil Docket, Cases 805-1122 (Box 5)
    - Civil Docket, Cases 1120-1222 (Box 6)
    - Civil Docket, Cases 1224-1338 (Box 7)
    - Civil Docket, Cases 1343-2077 (Box 8)
    - Civil Docket, Cases 5403/4-5876 (Box 9)
    - Three Judge Courts (Box 10)
    - Criminal Docket (Box 10)
- Court of Appeals 1971-1973
  The series begins with proceedings of the Three Judge Court. The Panel Reports of the Court of Appeals include the recommended disposition of petitions for review of lower court or administrative agency cases. Unpublished Opinions include decided case opinions that were not published in a standard case reporter. The Judicial Council files include documents relating to the administration of justice within the circuit relating to practice and procedure. The Judges Memoranda are the drafts of opinions of cases heard by the Court of Appeals and reflect the agreement, disagreement and suggested changes to the opinion by various members of the Court of Appeals Panel which heard the case.
  - Judge's Case Files
    - Three Judge Court Proceedings (Box 11)
    - Three Judge Court Proceedings (Box 12)
    - Panel Reports 1971-1973 (Box 13)
    - Panel Reports 1973 (Box 14)
    - Special Panels (Box 14)
    - Unpublished Opinions and Orders (Kent) (Box 14)
    - Circuit Council Meetings (Box 14)
    - Hearing Memoranda, Orders, and Opinions December 1971-April 1972 (Box 15)
    - Hearing Memoranda, Orders, and Opinions (Box 16)
      - 20,761-20,762 (Box 16)
      - 71-1,000; 21,001-71-1001 20,725-21,000; 18,000-20,724; 20,692- (Box 17)
      - 72-1800-; 72-1450-; 72-(); 72-1450 71-1800 71-1600 71-1000-; 72-1078- (Box 18)
      - K Panels; 71-1105-; 71-1220-;71-1415- (Box 19)